Fear can hold you prisoner. Hope can set you free.
The Shawshank Redemption is a drama, crime film directed by Frank Darabont.
Imprisoned in the 1940s for the double murder of his wife and her lover, upstanding banker Andy Dufresne begins a
new life at the Shawshank prison, where he puts his accounting skills to work for an amoral warden.
During his long stretch in prison, Dufresne comes to be admired by the other inmates -- including
an older prisoner named Red -- for his integrity and unquenchable sense of hope.
Andy Dufresne, played by Tim Robbins.
Ellis Boyd 'Red' Redding, played by Morgan Freeman.
Warden Norton, played by Bob Gunton.
Heywood, played by William Sadler.
Captain Byron T. Hadley, played by Clancy Brown.
Tommy, played by Gil Bellows.
The Shawshank Redemption is a 1994 American drama film written and directed by Frank Darabont,
based on the 1982 Stephen King novella Rita Hayworth and Shawshank Redemption.
The film tells the story of banker Andy Dufresne (Tim Robbins), who is sentenced to life in Shawshank State
Penitentiary for the murders of his wife and her lover, despite his claims of innocence.
Over the following two decades, he befriends a fellow prisoner, contraband smuggler Ellis "Red" Redding (Morgan Freeman),
and becomes instrumental in a money laundering operation led by the prison warden Samuel Norton (Bob Gunton).
William Sadler, Clancy Brown, Gil Bellows, and James
Whitmore appear in supporting roles.
Darabont purchased the film rights to King's story in 1987, but development did not
begin until five years later, when he wrote the script over eight weeks.
Two weeks after submitting his script to Castle Rock Entertainment, Darabont secured a $25 million
budget to produce The Shawshank Redemption, which started pre-production in January 1993.
While the film is set in Maine, principal photography took place from June to August 1993 almost entirely
in Mansfield, Ohio, with the Ohio State Reformatory serving as the eponymous penitentiary.
The project attracted many stars for the role of Andy,
including Tom Hanks, Tom Cruise, and Kevin Costner.
Thomas Newman provided the film's score.
The Shawshank Redemption premiered at the Toronto International Film Festival on
September 10, 1994, and was released by Columbia Pictures on September 23, 1994.
While the film received critical acclaim upon its release—particularly for its story and the performances of Robbins and
Freeman—it was a box-office disappointment, earning only $16 million during its initial theatrical run.
Its failure was attributed at the time to many factors, including competition from the films Pulp Fiction and Forrest Gump, the general
unpopularity of prison films, its lack of female characters, and even the title, which was considered confusing for audiences.
It went on to receive multiple award nominations, including seven Academy Award nominations, and a theatrical
re-release that, combined with international takings, increased the film's box-office gross to $73.3 million.
Over 320,000 VHS rental copies were shipped throughout the United States, and on the strength of
its award nominations and word of mouth, it became the top video rental of 1995.
The broadcast rights were acquired following the purchase of Castle Rock Entertainment by Turner Broadcasting System,
and it was shown regularly on the TNT network starting in 1997, further increasing its popularity.
Decades after release, the film is still broadcast regularly and is popular in several countries, with audience members and celebrities citing it as a
source of inspiration or naming it a favorite in various surveys, leading to its recognition as one of the most beloved films among audiences.
In 2015, the United States Library of Congress selected the film for preservation in the National
Film Registry, finding it "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of prison, friendship, police
brutality, corruption, based on novel or book.
The tone is dark and emotional.